<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>The Confluence Projects</title>
<link>http://www.confluence-project.org/rn.html</link>
<atom:link href="http://www.confluence-project.org/rn.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>A great sample blog</description>
<generator>quarto-1.2.313</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Sun, 14 Jan 2024 05:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>What is ‘Apparent Temperature’?</title>
  <dc:creator>Pedram Fard and Chirag Patel</dc:creator>
  <link>http://www.confluence-project.org/posts/what_is_at.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>In a <a href="./intro_gridex.html">few</a> <a href="./extreme_heat_california.html">of</a> our posts, we talk a lot about “<strong>apparent temperature</strong>”. What is it and how is it calculated?</p>
<p>While different measures have been developed in epidemiological research to quantify heat and cold exposure, a composite is a solution for extreme heat and cold exposure assessment.</p>
<p>We used the apparent temperature (AT) as it allows for a holistic representation of thermal comfort and perceived temperature by incorporating factors such as relative humidity and wind speed in addition to the ambient temperature.</p>
<p>AT is derived through a linear combination of actual temperature, vapor pressure and wind speed in metric units and interpreted in Celsius (°C), where:</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?AT%20=%20%E2%88%922.7%20+%201.04T%20+%202.0P%20%E2%88%92%200.65u"></p>
<p>AT: Apparent Temperature Index in °C<br>
T: Temperature in °C<br>
P: Vapor pressure in kPa<br>
u: Wind speed in m/s</p>
<section id="references" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="references">References</h2>
<p><a href="http://paperpile.com/b/r994tT/XWgx">Spangler KR, Liang S, Wellenius GA. Wet-Bulb Globe Temperature, Universal Thermal Climate Index, and Other Heat Metrics for US Counties, 2000–2020. Scientific Data. 2022 Jun 17;9(1):1–9.</a></p>
<p><a href="http://paperpile.com/b/r994tT/ZmjT">Steadman RG. A Universal Scale of Apparent Temperature. J Appl Meteorol Climatol. 1984 Dec 1;23(12):1674–87.</a></p>
<p><a href="http://paperpile.com/b/r994tT/josx">Sheridan SC, Lee CC, Allen MJ. The Mortality Response to Absolute and Relative Temperature Extremes. Int J Environ Res Public Health [Internet]. 2019 Apr 27;16(9). Available from:</a><a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.3390/ijerph16091493" class="uri">http://dx.doi.org/10.3390/ijerph16091493</a></p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>apparent temperature</category>
  <guid>http://www.confluence-project.org/posts/what_is_at.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 14 Jan 2024 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Hands on tutorials at the PAA</title>
  <dc:creator>Pedram Fard, Hossein Estiri, and Chirag Patel</dc:creator>
  <link>http://www.confluence-project.org/posts/paa.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-right" style="float: right;">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://www.confluence-project.org/posts/img/grid_ohio.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="PAA Ohio" width="300"></p>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Interested in the data we are creating? Come join us at PAA to get a hands-on overview!</p>
<ul>
<li>Dates: April 17-20, 2024</li>
<li>Location: Columbus, Ohio</li>
<li>Conference website: <a href="https://www.populationassociation.org/paa2024/home" class="uri">https://www.populationassociation.org/paa2024/home</a></li>
</ul>
<section id="organizers" class="level1">
<h1>Organizers:</h1>
<ul>
<li>Pedram Fard, Department of Biomedical Informatics, Harvard Medical School, USA</li>
<li>Risto Conte Keivabu, Max Planck Institute for Demographic Research (MPIDR), Germany</li>
<li>Vy Kim Nguyen, Department of Biomedical Informatics, Harvard Medical School, USA</li>
<li>Hossein Estiri, Department of Medicine, Harvard Medical School, USA</li>
<li>Chirag J Patel, Department of Biomedical Informatics, Harvard Medical School, USA</li>
<li>Contact person: Pedram Fard (Pedram_Fard<at>hms.harvard.edu)</at></li>
</ul>
<p>Extreme climate events are increasingly recognized as associated with adverse health outcomes as well as broad range social and economic impacts. While impacts on health is a major area of investigation within the scientific community, demographic repercussions of climate events remain elusive. To facilitate evaluating the spatio-temporal patterns and assess disparities of extreme climate impacts, we have developed a geoinformatics pipeline and curated a longitudinal dataset of precise extreme heat and cold events (EHEs/ECEs) in the United States, at a very fine spatial and temporal resolution (500×500-meter grids). We will present this data source, which is publicly available to the scientific community, and provide tutorials on how to access and address different demographic and epidemiological research questions.</p>
<section id="workshop-objectives-and-outcomes" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="workshop-objectives-and-outcomes">Workshop objectives and outcomes:</h2>
<p>The objective of this workshop is to equip researchers with theoretical concepts and analytical instruments for evaluating the impact of EHE/ECE on demographic outcomes including morbidity, mortality and migration. The workshop helps participants to get started with querying and retrieving the national dataset of EHE/ECE covering the continental United States over the past 15 years. They will also gain experience in linking this catalog with other data sources such as Census ACS. By participating in this workshop, the attendees would be better able to: Learn about opportunities, challenges and possible solutions in leveraging large scale spatio-temporal data for population-based epidemiological health research. Understand the considerations in integrating, maintaining and retrieval of climatological and socio-demographic data from dispersed and heterogeneous data sources. Learn the sources of uncertainty in identifying extreme climate events and the exposed population in such incidents, and understand strategies to minimize the errors in the impacted population classifications. Formulate their personalized approach to adoption of geoinformatics technology and open source softwares for climate related demographic research.</p>
</section>
<section id="workshop-activities-and-schedule" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="workshop-activities-and-schedule">Workshop activities and schedule:</h2>
<p>The half-day workshop is divided into four sections that provide both theoretical approaches and hands-on activities.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>First, we offer an introduction to population-based epidemiology followed by an overview of extreme climate events research, and population dynamics analysis (45 minutes).</p></li>
<li><p>Second, we review the climatological and demographic data sources and present the geo-informatics pipeline and dataset we have developed for augmented mapping of the extreme heat and cold exposure assessment using historical weather data provided by NOAA ISD (45 minutes).</p></li>
<li><p>Third, we illustrate the process of connecting the catalog of EHEs/ECEs with ACS, and examining the demographic characteristics of the affected population at the census tract level (45 minutes). Lastly, the workshop concludes with a hands-on tutorial on identifying geographic regions and populations affected by extreme heat and cold events using the R programming suite (75 minutes).</p></li>
</ol>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>news</category>
  <guid>http://www.confluence-project.org/posts/paa.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2024 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://www.confluence-project.org/posts/img/grid_ohio.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="144" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Introducing GridEX for extreme events</title>
  <dc:creator>Pedram Fard</dc:creator>
  <link>http://www.confluence-project.org/posts/intro_gridex.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p><img src="http://www.confluence-project.org/posts/img/grid.png" class="img-fluid" style="float: right;" data-fig-align="right" alt="PAA Ohio" width="300"> Accurate attribution of the areas and populations impacted by climate-related events often relies on distance-based methodologies in which the population of the study unit is assigned temperature data to the closest weather station. We have developed a method that provides a grid-based measure of exposure to extreme heat and cold events called Grid EXposure (GridEX). This approach allows for capturing a more comprehensive representation of thermal comfort and the perceived temperature. GridEX leverages a data science pipeline to gather station-based climatological data and estimate fine-resolution surfaces of ambient (i.e., the air temperature at 2m above the land surface) and apparent temperature (i.e., the perceived temperature by humans, which takes into account humidity and wind in addition to the actual air temperature) with 500x500m resolution. We validated GridEX against station temperature observations from the NOAA Integrated Surface Database (ISD) and re-analysis climate data provided by GridMET. All the derivative data and the associated source code are publicly available.</p>
<section id="pipeline-schematic" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pipeline-schematic">Pipeline schematic</h2>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://www.confluence-project.org/posts/img/pipeline.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<p></p><figcaption class="figure-caption">Figure 1. Pipeline to call EHE and ECE</figcaption><p></p>
</figure>
</div>
<p>We have developed our dataset in a sequential process illustrated in Fig 1:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>Data Acquisition: We retrieved a substantial dataset comprising over 800 million historical records of hourly and sub-hourly ambient temperature, dew point, and wind speed, recorded at nearly 2,250 weather stations and provided by NOAA (Fig 1a).</p></li>
<li><p>Daily meteorological parameters computation: We computed the daily average values for ambient temperature, vapor pressure, and wind speed by taking the mean of hourly and sub-hourly raw data at station locations (Fig 1b).</p></li>
<li><p>Missing data imputation: We detected and imputed missing daily records of up to five days gap in the daily time series based on the historical data from the same location (Fig 1c).</p></li>
<li><p>Apparent temperature computation: We calculated the average daily apparent temperature (AT) for each station using the method developed by Steadman (Fig 1c). What is AT? <a href="./what_is_at.html">Check out our post</a>!</p></li>
<li><p>Excess heat and cold factor computation: We began the extreme event delineation by determining the excess heat and cold factors (EHF/ECF) as measures of temperature anomaly against historical normals (Fig 1d). We identified anomalies by contrasting the rolling average AT of the immediate past three days with the rolling average AT observed during the 30 days leading up to those three days at each station location</p></li>
<li><p>Station-based extreme events identification: Leveraging the EHF/ECF, we identified the instances of extreme heat and cold events at the station locations using relative thresholds according to Sheridan et al.&nbsp;(Fig 1e).</p></li>
<li><p>Extreme events intensity measurement: Using the station-based EHE/ECE daily records, we quantified the intensity of these extreme events by multiplying the duration of extreme heat or cold episodes and their levels of excess heat and cold. As suggested by Fard et al., the resulting Extreme Heat and Cold Magnitude Indicators (EHMI/ECMI) can be used to quantitatively compare the strength of EHE/ECE across geographies, where values closer to zero indicate locations minimally impacted by short-lived extreme conditions. In contrast, values approaching +100 pinpoint the prolonged heat events, and those nearing -100 signify places affected by extended cold events (Fig 1f).</p></li>
<li><p>Spatial interpolation: Based on the intensity values derived for station locations, we spatially interpolated EHMI/ECMI values across the contiguous United States using the inverse distance weighted (IDW) method over a high-resolution spatial grid (Fig 1g). IDW was used to assign weights to nearby stations’ measurements (i.e., EHMI/ECMI) inversely proportional to their distances to each grid cell. The weighted values were then averaged to estimate the EHMI/ECMI values for every grid cell, generating the continuous surface.</p></li>
<li><p>Area-wide extreme events determination: Finally, by analyzing the interpolated grids of EHMI/ECMI, we outlined the geographic extent of extreme events daily (Fig 1h).</p></li>
</ol>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://www.confluence-project.org/posts/img/gridex_fig2.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<p></p><figcaption class="figure-caption">Figure 2. Statistical distribution of the computed AT for all the stations within the study area (2008 - 2022). The solid red line indicates the overall mean, and the dashed green line denotes the overall median value.</figcaption><p></p>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://www.confluence-project.org/posts/img/gridex_fig3.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<p></p><figcaption class="figure-caption">Figure 3. Schematic illustration of the meteorological data processes from computing daily values of AT to estimate spatial surface of the extreme events intensity and the delineating the area-wide EHE/ECE boundaries</figcaption><p></p>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="data-and-code-resources" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="data-and-code-resources">Data and Code Resources</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Fard et al., <strong>GridEX: A Dataset for Assessing the Area-wide Extreme Heat and Cold Exposure in the United States: 2008-2022</strong> (Submitted)</p>
<ul>
<li><p><strong>Github</strong>: <a href="https://github.com/epedram/us_ehe_ece" class="uri">https://github.com/epedram/us_ehe_ece</a></p></li>
<li><p><strong>Data (Dataverse)</strong>: <a href="https://dataverse.harvard.edu/dataset.xhtml?persistentId=doi:10.7910/DVN/DJGKDJ" class="uri">https://dataverse.harvard.edu/dataset.xhtml?persistentId=doi:10.7910/DVN/DJGKDJ</a>.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Data (Figshare)</strong>: <a href="https://figshare.com/s/aab128348a1d0c8a4988/articles/24993447" class="uri">https://figshare.com/s/aab128348a1d0c8a4988/articles/24993447</a></p></li>
</ul></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>news</category>
  <category>gridex</category>
  <category>extreme events</category>
  <guid>http://www.confluence-project.org/posts/intro_gridex.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2024 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://www.confluence-project.org/posts/img/grid.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="144" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Estimating Extreme Heat Events in California</title>
  <dc:creator>Pedram Fard</dc:creator>
  <link>http://www.confluence-project.org/posts/extreme_heat_california.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://www.confluence-project.org/posts/img/california_dalle.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<p></p><figcaption class="figure-caption">A striking illustration representing extreme heat in California. The scene depicts a vast Californian landscape under a blazing sun, with clear signs. Image courtesy of DALL-E (GPT-4, 1/12/24).</figcaption><p></p>
</figure>
</div>
<section id="summary" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="summary">Summary</h2>
<p>Studying how climate change affects us requires accurately identifying areas hit by extreme weather, like intense heat waves. Usually, researchers estimate these conditions using data from the nearest weather station, but this method can be inaccurate. A new approach has been developed that better tracks Extreme Heat Events by using a more detailed temperature measure. This improved method is much more precise, correctly identifying about one million more Californians affected by severe heat each day between 2017 and 2021, compared to the old way.</p>
</section>
<section id="highlights" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="highlights">Highlights</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>Our proposed method uses spatial interpolation to accurately estimate EHE boundaries.</p></li>
<li><p>The conventional methods rely on absolute temperature and larger spatial scales.</p></li>
<li><p>Our method accounts for antecedent climate conditions and composite heat measure.</p></li>
<li><p>Our method significantly reduces misclassification of populations impacted by EHEs.</p></li>
</ul>
<section id="overview" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="overview">Overview</h3>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://www.confluence-project.org/posts/img/ca_fig2.jpeg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<p></p><figcaption class="figure-caption">Integrating modalities while considering missing data from NOAA. Figure presents an example of missingness patterns for a certain station, along with the derived Apparent Temperature (AT) computed based on the imputed missing values. Red lines denote missing data; blue points denote non-missing daily data points.</figcaption><p></p>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://www.confluence-project.org/posts/img/ca_fig3.jpeg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<p></p><figcaption class="figure-caption">Apparent temperature (AT) estimated for the held-out test set stations (blank rectangles) using the training set (solid circles) daily records. Plot A (left) shows the uniform spatial surface estimation method. Plot B (right) depicts the spatial interpolation. The regions in shades of blue represent areas with colder AT, while the areas in red represent warmer temperatures.</figcaption><p></p>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://www.confluence-project.org/posts/img/ca_fig4.jpeg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<p></p><figcaption class="figure-caption">Number of distinct EHE days impacted an area, along with the spatial distribution and proportion of land areas impacted by at least one EHE (2017–2021). Percent of the land surface impacted by at least one EHE presented in parentheses</figcaption><p></p>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
</section>
<section id="citation" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="citation">Citation:</h2>
<p><a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0013935123017887">Fard et al., Spatio-temporal interpolation and delineation of extreme heat events in California between 2017 and 2021, <em>Environmental Research</em> 2022</a></p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>news</category>
  <category>california</category>
  <guid>http://www.confluence-project.org/posts/extreme_heat_california.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2023 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://www.confluence-project.org/posts/img/california_dalle.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="144" width="144"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
