<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>The Confluence Projects</title>
<link>http://www.confluence-project.org/rn.html</link>
<atom:link href="http://www.confluence-project.org/rn.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>A great sample blog</description>
<generator>quarto-1.2.313</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2024 05:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Hands on tutorials at the PAA</title>
  <dc:creator>Pedram Fard, Hossein Estiri, and Chirag Patel</dc:creator>
  <link>http://www.confluence-project.org/posts/paa.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-right" style="float: right;">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://www.confluence-project.org/posts/img/grid_ohio.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="PAA Ohio" width="300"></p>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Interested in the data we are creating? Come join us at PAA to get a hands-on overview!</p>
<ul>
<li>Dates: April 17-20, 2024</li>
<li>Location: Columbus, Ohio</li>
<li>Conference website: <a href="https://www.populationassociation.org/paa2024/home" class="uri">https://www.populationassociation.org/paa2024/home</a></li>
</ul>
<section id="organizers" class="level1">
<h1>Organizers:</h1>
<ul>
<li>Pedram Fard, Department of Biomedical Informatics, Harvard Medical School, USA</li>
<li>Risto Conte Keivabu, Max Planck Institute for Demographic Research (MPIDR), Germany</li>
<li>Vy Kim Nguyen, Department of Biomedical Informatics, Harvard Medical School, USA</li>
<li>Hossein Estiri, Department of Medicine, Harvard Medical School, USA</li>
<li>Chirag J Patel, Department of Biomedical Informatics, Harvard Medical School, USA</li>
<li>Contact person: Pedram Fard (Pedram_Fard<at>hms.harvard.edu)</at></li>
</ul>
<p>Extreme climate events are increasingly recognized as associated with adverse health outcomes as well as broad range social and economic impacts. While impacts on health is a major area of investigation within the scientific community, demographic repercussions of climate events remain elusive. To facilitate evaluating the spatio-temporal patterns and assess disparities of extreme climate impacts, we have developed a geoinformatics pipeline and curated a longitudinal dataset of precise extreme heat and cold events (EHEs/ECEs) in the United States, at a very fine spatial and temporal resolution (500×500-meter grids). We will present this data source, which is publicly available to the scientific community, and provide tutorials on how to access and address different demographic and epidemiological research questions.</p>
<section id="workshop-objectives-and-outcomes" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="workshop-objectives-and-outcomes">Workshop objectives and outcomes:</h2>
<p>The objective of this workshop is to equip researchers with theoretical concepts and analytical instruments for evaluating the impact of EHE/ECE on demographic outcomes including morbidity, mortality and migration. The workshop helps participants to get started with querying and retrieving the national dataset of EHE/ECE covering the continental United States over the past 15 years. They will also gain experience in linking this catalog with other data sources such as Census ACS. By participating in this workshop, the attendees would be better able to: Learn about opportunities, challenges and possible solutions in leveraging large scale spatio-temporal data for population-based epidemiological health research. Understand the considerations in integrating, maintaining and retrieval of climatological and socio-demographic data from dispersed and heterogeneous data sources. Learn the sources of uncertainty in identifying extreme climate events and the exposed population in such incidents, and understand strategies to minimize the errors in the impacted population classifications. Formulate their personalized approach to adoption of geoinformatics technology and open source softwares for climate related demographic research.</p>
</section>
<section id="workshop-activities-and-schedule" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="workshop-activities-and-schedule">Workshop activities and schedule:</h2>
<p>The half-day workshop is divided into four sections that provide both theoretical approaches and hands-on activities.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>First, we offer an introduction to population-based epidemiology followed by an overview of extreme climate events research, and population dynamics analysis (45 minutes).</p></li>
<li><p>Second, we review the climatological and demographic data sources and present the geo-informatics pipeline and dataset we have developed for augmented mapping of the extreme heat and cold exposure assessment using historical weather data provided by NOAA ISD (45 minutes).</p></li>
<li><p>Third, we illustrate the process of connecting the catalog of EHEs/ECEs with ACS, and examining the demographic characteristics of the affected population at the census tract level (45 minutes). Lastly, the workshop concludes with a hands-on tutorial on identifying geographic regions and populations affected by extreme heat and cold events using the R programming suite (75 minutes).</p></li>
</ol>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>news</category>
  <guid>http://www.confluence-project.org/posts/paa.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2024 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://www.confluence-project.org/posts/img/grid_ohio.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="144" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Introducing GridEX for extreme events</title>
  <dc:creator>Pedram Fard</dc:creator>
  <link>http://www.confluence-project.org/posts/intro_gridex.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p><img src="http://www.confluence-project.org/posts/img/grid.png" class="img-fluid" style="float: right;" data-fig-align="right" alt="PAA Ohio" width="300"> Accurate attribution of the areas and populations impacted by climate-related events often relies on distance-based methodologies in which the population of the study unit is assigned temperature data to the closest weather station. We have developed a method that provides a grid-based measure of exposure to extreme heat and cold events called Grid EXposure (GridEX). This approach allows for capturing a more comprehensive representation of thermal comfort and the perceived temperature. GridEX leverages a data science pipeline to gather station-based climatological data and estimate fine-resolution surfaces of ambient (i.e., the air temperature at 2m above the land surface) and apparent temperature (i.e., the perceived temperature by humans, which takes into account humidity and wind in addition to the actual air temperature) with 500x500m resolution. We validated GridEX against station temperature observations from the NOAA Integrated Surface Database (ISD) and re-analysis climate data provided by GridMET. All the derivative data and the associated source code are publicly available.</p>
<section id="pipeline-schematic" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pipeline-schematic">Pipeline schematic</h2>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://www.confluence-project.org/posts/img/pipeline.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<p></p><figcaption class="figure-caption">Pipeline to call EHE and ECE</figcaption><p></p>
</figure>
</div>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>news</category>
  <category>gridex</category>
  <category>extreme events</category>
  <guid>http://www.confluence-project.org/posts/intro_gridex.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2024 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://www.confluence-project.org/posts/img/grid.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="144" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Estimating Extreme Heat Events in California</title>
  <dc:creator>Pedram Fard</dc:creator>
  <link>http://www.confluence-project.org/posts/extreme_heat_california.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="http://www.confluence-project.org/posts/img/california_dalle.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<p></p><figcaption class="figure-caption">A striking illustration representing extreme heat in California. The scene depicts a vast Californian landscape under a blazing sun, with clear signs. Image courtesy of DALL-E (GPT-4, 1/12/24).</figcaption><p></p>
</figure>
</div>
<section id="summary" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="summary">Summary</h2>
<p>Studying how climate change affects us requires accurately identifying areas hit by extreme weather, like intense heat waves. Usually, researchers estimate these conditions using data from the nearest weather station, but this method can be inaccurate. A new approach has been developed that better tracks Extreme Heat Events by using a more detailed temperature measure. This improved method is much more precise, correctly identifying about one million more Californians affected by severe heat each day between 2017 and 2021, compared to the old way.</p>
</section>
<section id="section" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="section"></h2>
<p>Citation:</p>
<p><a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0013935123017887">Fard et al., Spatio-temporal interpolation and delineation of extreme heat events in California between 2017 and 2021, <em>Environmental Research</em> 2022</a></p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>news</category>
  <category>california</category>
  <guid>http://www.confluence-project.org/posts/extreme_heat_california.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2023 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://www.confluence-project.org/posts/img/california_dalle.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="144" width="144"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
